Amendment Bill. And our first submitter this afternoon is New Zealand
Fish and Game Council. Welcome, Carina. How's it going?
Kia ora.
Good.
Nice to be here. Thank you.
You've got 15 minutes with us, so take your submission as read-
Mm-hmm
... uh, and we'll hand it over to you to open up, and then we'll open up for
questions.
Oh, thank you very much. I've just got a, um, a short opening statement and, and
then I'll leave plenty of time for questions.
Um, kia ora koutou, and thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
My name's Carina Jordan, and I am the chief executive of the New Zealand Fish and
Game Council. Um, I've spoken to you all before, so, uh, I know that you know
who Fish and Game is. Statutory manager for sports fish and game birds, established
under the Conservation Act 1987. And we
represent around about 175,000 license holders, anglers, and
game bird hunters. So firstly, Fish and Game agrees that the
conservation framework needs to be modernized, and we welcome the
move to a more integrated and efficient system.
Obviously, this is where our statutory functions sit under the Conservation Act,
uh, so this is a process, um, that is highly relevant to the organization
and top of mind, um, for us at the moment, while we're also thinking about further
changes to the Wildlife Act and also consideration of a fish and game
bill on the future horizon.
The points I want to raise today are points we think may not have been fully worked
through as the bill was put together, rather than objections to what the
bill is trying to achieve. And so we're hoping our submission was seen in that
light and that has been helpful. And we look forward to continuing to work,
um, with the government, um, with the Minister for Conservation, and with the
Department of Conservation, um, on, uh, as the planning framework is
established through the National Conservation Policy Statement and
area plans.
Just a couple of points. Angling and game bird hunting value should be
recognized as distinct from recreation.
I set this out in quite a bit of detail within our submission.
This is really important because parts of the proposed changes to the
Conservation Act are significantly,
um, uh, walk across or step across
Fish and Game statutory, current statutory functions, the values of
sports fish and game birds, and our activities on the conservation
estate. And so we think some material changes are really required to
be made through the Amendment Bill to ensure that those statutory
functions are retained and those powers are retained by the organization.
Uh, we're seeking an amendment to Section 6A and Section 6EA
to recognize hunting and fishing values as standalone values, and I set that out in
more detail.
We're not recognized as partners in the new planning framework.
I've a little bit of alluded to that at the beginning.
It doesn't, um, through the framework, it enables the,
uh, Minister for Conservation to make decisions, but there's no requirement to
essentially consult with Fish and Game in relation to our values or the management
of sports fish or game bird, uh, populations through the provisions of the bill.
And this is further weakened by the way that our, our, um,
management plans, our sports fish and game bird management plans are treated by the
amendments through the bill as well.
So they become subservient to the higher level policies within the
Conservation Amendment, um, framework without
recognizing fishing or game bird hunting values as standalone values
in themselves.
The other one that we want to talk about is that our statutory functions shouldn't
require a concession. So we undertake game bird, um, monitoring and
sports fish monitoring within the conservation estate.
Things like electric fishing, um, looking at spawning surveys, and
also management over game bird populations, and we're wanting those to be exempted
from, uh, the requirement to have a concession.
So in closing, we support the bill as it's been set up to do.
Uh, us, a practical refinements that would make the framework work better for our
anglers and our hunters, um, and for the fisheries wetlands and access they depend
upon. And recognizing hunting and fishuring, fishing as distinct values bring
our management plans into the framework and make us a consul tee rather than
as an afterthought, I think will strengthen up the management of their species and
their habitats.
Brilliant. Thank you very much. Um, we will go first to Ryan
Hamilton for a question.
Thanks, Carina. Um, is your concern that this bill removes
existing rights and responsibilities, or that it fails to
explicitly provide for them in the proposed?
We think it weakens them by the changes that have been made.
We don't think that that's obviously intentional.
We think it's just a, a function of the amendments that have been put forward.
Okay.
Thank you.
And Grant.
Yeah. Just this one, um, the last point you made about exempting you from
the concession process. So, um,
if you were, how would you... Obviously, there's still gotta be a relationship with
DOC and gotta work with them. Um, how, how,
how would you envisage that would happen and, you know,
so that they don't get surprised if you're working and things in a space, you
know?
It would, uh, be undertaken as sort of it is, is at the moment where we can, um,
we engage directly with the DOC regional offices-
Yeah
... um, and essentially have a relationship with them whereby we can go in and
undertake those activities. They understand when we're in the conservation state
undertaking those activities, so it avoids, uh, conflict.
Hmm.
Okay.
I might just jump in and ask a question.
Because obviously, you get a lot of international visitors coming through and
fishing in the rivers, et cetera.
And obviously, that takes its toll on the DOC land and
huts and tracks and everything. Are you supportive of
being able to look at more development, I suppose, on DOC
land, and obviously, the international visitor levy being able to
use to be put back into work on the huts and tracks and
upkeeping a lot of the DOC estate?
Yes, definitely. What we know is that we need to invest in the DOC estate
to be able to manage it. The taxpayer money only goes so far.
Hmm
So looking at other economic opportunities for the conservation estate just makes
sense. I think our point of view is just that we should be consulted if it's
to do with excess of hunting and fishing or hunting and fishing
values and the management of those areas in relation to those values.
So that's our predominant ask. But essentially,
trying to create revenue and economic benefit from the conservation estate makes
sense to put that money back into conservation.
Can I just supplement?
Yes, go for it, Raj.
I was reading about your sports fish game management plans.
Yes
It's a new term for me.
Can you provide examples where they've provided or delivered environmental outcomes
that may not have otherwise been? Because I know it was similar, we talked before
about the HOSI, but is that a parallel, or can you give some evidence
of where those plans have actually enhanced environmental outcomes?
Yes. So, it's a little bit of a combination.
Wetlands are probably the one that comes immediately to mind.
So we've put about $20 million back into wetland restoration and enhancement across
New Zealand. So that's not only just on the...
It's partly in the conservation estate, but mostly outside of the conservation
estate. But that's one clear example about how-
Right
... implementation of our functions and the additional
license holder contribution can be
implemented on the ground in relation to habitat restoration.
Okay.
Thank you.
Grant.
Yes, up on that as well. You talk about here,
concessions and visitor amenity areas must
assess effects on hunting, angling, habitat, and access.
I'm just curious as to the access one, I think it's reasonably
self-explanatory, but in terms of the impact on the other issues,
what sort of impacts are you potentially seeing that will be created from
visitor amenity areas?
Well, our
main concern there is just to make sure that the hunting and fishing values are
recognized when considering visitor amenity
areas and how they will be managed and the relative impact that will have on
existing hunting and fishing. I think an example I've got is just, for example,
when we're thinking about changing land designations, stewardship land comes to
mind.
Mm-hmm.
The hunting and freshwater fishing values were supposed to be recognized, and
they were recognized to a certain extent.
But they weren't carried through to the re-designation of that land.
And so, through that process, we actually lost access and lost
a number of those hunting and fishing areas because of that land
designation. So our concern really is just that if you're changing the way that
land is considered or land is to be managed, then please consider the hunting and
fishing values and access to them in any management frameworks.
Brilliant. You've got another one, Grant.
I might just jump in-
There you go
... quickly. The 26
that you talk about here, do you want to just elaborate a little bit on that?
Because you've said that that is the most important provision, and it's
relatable to Fish and Game,
but we haven't had any other submissions yet that have raised that specific point,
so.
Yeah. Have you got what page are you looking at?
So I'm just on page two.
It's 26Q1.
Basically, where you're making some recommendations around
that. I'm just wondering whether...
I just don't quite understand
that particular recommendation that you're making.
Yeah. I'm just grabbing our detailed submission.
Because you talk about it, but I'm just wondering what your-
You're asking
... what you're specifically asking there to be actually changed
within the legislation itself.
Just because obviously that's quite unique and specific
to Fish and Game.
Helen, do you want to jump on there while I grab it?
Oh, Helen-
She's grabbing it too
... you're just on mute there.
There we go.
I'm just looking it up in the table at the end, Carina.
Oh, is there a table? I don't think we've got a table.
No. 26Q functions of fishing.
Yeah. At the end of the submission, page 47, there's a
table with suggested changes, amendments.
Oh, I'm not sure I got that on my-
We've only got a four-pager.
We've got 13 pages.
No, the full submission is 59 pages.
Oh, that explains.
Oh, okay. We were not given that submission.
So we've got a detailed appendix which sets out
clause by clause the specific changes that we're wanting to make to the
provisions.
Okay.
We can recirculate that.
Do you want to send that perhaps through to us?
Because we've only got-
I've only got 13
...
the short. We've got a 13-page
submission.
Summary.
That says-
But 26Q was about the functions of Fishing Game Council.
Yes.
What was the submission about around that?
Yeah. We might need to get that thorough full submission that obviously
we don't have.
But we've got the summary.
Sorry, I can't find it in the table.
That's okay. If you want to come back to us on that.
That was just-
I should be able to-
... a particular main area that you wanted us to address within the legislation, so
that's why I was just keen to understand a little bit more about it
Yeah. I'll try and do that off the top of my head with that, but we'll
circulate. You should have the detailed submission in front of you, so we'll make
sure that that gets pre-circulated to you.
But essentially, the main thing is the linking Fish and Game statutory functions
under Section 26 of the Conservation Act through to the Amendment Bill.
And so the main ones, as I was talking about, is recognizing sports, fishing, game
birds-
Yeah
... their habitats, and then the role of Fish and Game in managing them.
Okay.
So that's sort of at a nutshell, which is the main point of the submission.
Yeah, so to make sure that's transferred over to-
Yes
... and recognizes that within the Amendment Bill.
Yes, that's right. And carried right through.
So, I can give you it clause by clause, but it talks to a number of amendments-
Yes
... through the proposed changes to the Conservation Act.
Okay. No, that's helpful. Thank you. Grant?
Yeah, just a question I want to raise with you.
Obviously, there was a lot of discussion, controversy around the whole concept of
the sale and swapping of land.
Have you guys got a strong view on that?
I'm just-- Where did Fish and Game sit on
that whole concept of DoP being able to sell or swap land?
I appreciate that this has been a fraught topic.
I've seen it play out through social media.
Our position is that we're not opposed to disposals at all.
We understand that there is a need for the Department of Conservation to be able to
exchange or dispose land.
Mm.
Our main concern is that if disposals are being considered, that access to
hunting and fishing areas are retained in consideration of those disposals.
Mm.
So, that's the main concern we're hearing from our hunters and our anglers.
The primary issue for hunting and angling is still access-
Mm
... and it is retained as access.
Yeah. Just very brief sup on that, because
for you, it's more about the process of making sure that the process would include
consulting with the groups that you represent, basically.
That's right. One of the amendments that we've sought is for the Minister
for Conservation to consult with Fish and Game in considering our
values, how those values are treated, and also if disposals are
being considered. And then we can talk to the minister or talk to the Department of
Conservation about the values, the
level of those values, where there are high values or what, and then what is
required to retain those values. Often it's access, but access can be
provided for through disposals like, for example, using esplanade reserves or
strips.
Yeah.
So it's often not just the area of the land, but if you take that land out, then
it's the access through that land to a resource-
Mm
... that's a major issue. Yeah.
Fish and Game's been successful in doing that.
Yeah.
Yes. So we have. So we've got a great example of that that's been run by the
Auckland-Waikato Fish and Game Council, where they bought a piece of land
to put an enduring access to a resource, and then the idea
being that as they sell that land back off, retaining that access for current and
future generations.
Yeah, I was going to ask for an example, but you've obviously-
Yes
... just given a good example of-
Mm. And we think that's a great blueprint for the future as well, and it means that
hunters and anglers are actually putting in access not only for them, but also for
our wider community, and it's funded by the license holder.
Absolutely. Brilliant. Hey, thank you very much for your-
That's great
... submission today. Appreciate you coming in in person as well.
And, yes, we will fish out the find
the pun, the full submission,
and work out what's happened there potentially.
It's swimming around somewhere.
Swimming around somewhere.
Right.
Hey, thank you very much, Karina. Appreciate your time today and your
thorough submission there.
Thanks.
So, we now welcome through our next submission for
today, the Environmental Defense Society, and
they are going to be joining us via Zoom, I
understand.
So we will just wait for them to pop up. There we go. Shaye, we can see you.
Welcome to the select committee this afternoon.
You have 15 minutes with us.
We have read your submission. It is a very thorough submission, so do take it as
read, and
we'll hand over to you to open up and then open for questions.
Thank you. Good afternoon, Madam Chair and members of the committee.
Thank you for providing EDS with this opportunity to present today.
My name is Shaye Schlaefer. I'm EDS's Chief Operating Officer
and General Counsel.
I want to start by saying that EDS is
opposed to the bill in its current form,
but we believe it can be fixed. The bill is
not beyond repair.
We think that amending the bill and panel beating it into
shape would be a better outcome than binning it
altogether.
Conservation law reform is required.
However, we have several big-ticket issues with the bill
that need amendment before we can support it, and these
are outlined in our submission, and I address four of them today.
We've chosen not to focus on exchange and disposals,
because the minister has already said that those provisions
should be pulled. So, the first issue I want
to discuss is the economic opportunities clauses,
and that's new Section 6EA, which has been discussed
a lot with other submitters. But also the corresponding
sections in 13D2,
13H2B, and in Section 14,
relating to the purpose of the National Conservation Policy
Statement, area plans, and the concessions framework.
Our first preference is that these clauses be deleted.
Alternatively, we have provided some acceptable
redrafting in our submission.
Key here is to delete the words "to the greatest
extent practicable,"
and make references to use and development consistent
with conservation.
And I've watched all of the other submitters who have presented to you to
date, and it seems that is a universal request.
Without those changes, the economic clauses place use
and development before conservation.
And that is because DOC functions have no hierarchy
which prioritize conservation imperatives.
The words "to enable use and development to the greatest extent
practical" are an open-ended maximizing
direction,
and because there is no corresponding conservation
direction in those other clauses I just referred to,
to counter the economic purpose of the
conservation policy statement area plans and the
concessions framework.
Cabinet was very clear that economic development was to
be provided only to the extent that it is
consistent with conservation.
We want to make it clear that does not mean balancing
conservation and economic development.
A balancing approach was expressly discounted as an
option by Cabinet.
So we're simply asking the select committee to give effect to Cabinet's
direction to prioritize conservation.
The second issue is with visitor amenity areas.
EDS supports VAA's in principle as
a strategic tool for managing visitors.
However, as drafted, the VAA
framework under the bill is not consistent with
conservation.
And that is reflected in a few different places.
The purpose statement for visitor amenity areas,
the broad list of activities that are provided for,
that visitor amenity areas operate as an override of area
plans, and the conservation purpose for which the land is
held,
that the assessment of VAAs is focused on the parent
land, which has the potential of minimizing impacts that
are actually significant at the estate scale,
and finally, that public input on the development of VAAs is
limited.
So in that context, we have considerable concern with
the minister's decision-making powers for VAAs.
There are simply not enough conservation guardrails to
ensure that the minister's decisions on
VAAs is required to prioritize conservation
values and imperatives.
And we've set out in our submission the amendments that we think are
required to the VAA framework to bring it into an
acceptable position.
The third issue I want to highlight is the centralization of
decision-making power with the minister and the
corresponding reduction in the roles of the Conservation
Authority and conservation boards.
EDS does not think that streamlining the conservation system
requires removing those checks and balances.
The Conservation Authority provides independent
national level expertise and oversight,
and conservation boards bring local knowledge and provide an important
connection between conservation decision making and the
communities that are affected by it.
So under the bill, those roles are significantly diminished while the
minister assumes greater control over conservation management
planning.
And that is particularly concerning when combined with the economic
development imperative and the broad VAA powers that I've just
discussed.
Those changes all pull in the same direction, which is
greater scope for development, coupled with fewer
independent and place-based checks on how those powers are
exercised.
We support streamlining the planning system, but streamlining should mean
removing unnecessary complexity and delay, not removing
conservation guardrails.
We therefore recommend retaining a meaningful decision-making
role for the Conservation Authority and conservation boards
within the new planning framework.
And the final issue I want to address relates to climate change.
So the bill is silent on climate change
considerations, and that has also flowed through into
the conservation policy, the first draft of that.
And we think that is a significant omission for a law that is
intended to provide a new framework for managing the
conservation estate for decades to come.
Climate change is already affecting conservation management.
It's changing where species can survive, it's
increasing pressure on vulnerable ecosystems, and it's
increasing risks to DOC assets and infrastructure.
And I know that one of the members referred to the Cathedral Cove
scenario, which is a prime example of this.
So new planning and concession systems need to be able to
respond to those changes. We recommend that the bill
integrate climate change considerations into the planning and concessions
framework. And again, our submission sets out
how we recommend that occur.
So to sum up, EDS supports reform of the conservation
system. There are real problems with the current system, and there is a
lot in this bill that provides a good foundation for change.
But the fundamental principle of any new conservation law must remain
clear that conservation comes first, and we
don't think that the bill as introduced achieves that.
We're happy to take questions.
Brilliant. Thank you very much, Shay.
I've got a question just in relation to conservation boards,
because that's been raised quite a bit throughout the
submission process. You also raise it
in your
submission, and you've just touched on the
concentration of power with the minister, which obviously
concerns you. What's your
specific solution in relation to that?
Well, we would like to bring back the decision-making role
of the Conservation Authority and the boards that has been stripped out of the
bill.
Awesome.
Yeah. Okay. So, that would be what you would want to see
through this process. Grant-
Yeah
... has a supplementary on that.
I suppose my supplementary is around, so effectively what
the design's to do now is they've
still got to be consulted with the conservation authority, the boards, and
that information is obviously public information was provided through to the
minister. Why don't you see that as sufficient?
Given that the minister is ultimately responsible for the decisions that
the conservation authorities make.
Yes. Well,
there are kind of two elements to this.
So,
the first issue is that the framing of the bill does not put
conservation first. So, there is no certainty within
that framing that the minister's decisions will
prioritize conservation values.
And the second thing that I think has come through quite
clearly from other submitters who are much closer to the decision-making process
than EDS, like the Conservation Authority, Ngāi
Tahu, the tourism operators.
What I've heard quite clear from them is the importance of local decision-making in
terms of a check on the system and making sure that those
decisions actually endure. And so, we would like the
framing of the bill to change, and for that community role to be
strengthened.
Just-
Sup
... just a quick sup on that.
You say that the framing of the whole bill is not focused on
conservation, or words to that effect.
Well, actually, the original purpose still sits there in the original
title of the original act. It hasn't changed, and that conservation sits at
the top.
Mm-hmm.
So, I'm a bit bemused and confused by that statement.
There is no one single purpose in the Conservation Act,
so you have to interpret its purpose by looking at
various clauses together, and that includes
Section 6, DOC's functions, the definition of
conservation. There's a few other things in that mix.
The title of the act. But
there is no
prioritization of those functions.
So yes, while there is still a conservation function in there for DOC,
it does not sit above the economic
clause. And in fact, the words in those economic
opportunities
clauses, to the greatest extent practicable, to our
mind, actually require DOC to start from a position of needing
to grant approval, and instead of considering
whether that concession is an appropriate use in the first place.
So, I think it actually switches the whole framework around.
Thank you. Celia.
Thank you very much. And particularly thank you for giving us the
links to your previous documents about tourism and nature and
landscape. And I hope because they've been referred to here, we
may be able to use them later. But, my
particular question, you talk about the role for the
NZCA and for the conservation boards,
and you talk about commission of inquiry.
What sort of items would you imagine being set as
a commission of inquiry by the NZCA?
That's a great question, Celia. Anything that is
substantive. We've called
for commissions of inquiries recently for reviewing
the fisheries management system.
We've also had an independent inquiry into land use in
Tairāwhiti, so these are the big kind of national level issues that
affect
the conservation estate in this case.
Thank you.
Look, we've got time for one last question. Scott.
Thank you, Shay.
You've mentioned that we can panel beat this bill
into shape. So, do you think if we create the
hierarchy with the conservation guardrails at the very top,
that is going to be the
key? All the other points you've made, but that's
really the fundamental issue here, isn't it?
That we need to have a hierarchy with the conservation guardrails.
Or
is there something else that we need to get right?
I think there are three main
framing issues that need to be changed in the bill, and you're quite right,
the economic opportunities clauses, not just in 6EA, but
the subsequential ones as well. That needs to be
fixed, and I think you've heard quite clearly, and we have drafting on how you
could do that. The visitor amenity framework
almost sits as an independent tool above
the system. So, that needs to be integrated back into it, and
parts of that need to be tweaked as well to bring conservation to the
fore. And I think the final thing would be to elevate that
community voice, to make sure that there is that additional check.
Brilliant. Thank you very much, Shay, and thank you for your
submission and all of the points you've raised.
Really valuable feedback, so we appreciate that going through this process.
So, thank you.
Thank you
So now we move to our next submitter today, Electricity Sector and
Environment Group, who are with us in person.
Welcome, Martin and team, to the select
committee this afternoon, and thank you for also your very
thorough submission as well. Do take it as read, but you
do have 15 minutes with us. So we'll hand over to you to open up, and then
we'll have questions. Thank you.
Thank you, Chair. Good afternoon, members of the committee.
Yes, my name's Martin Williams, counsel for the Electricity Sector
Environment Group, or ESEG, as we call it.
I'm here with Christina Healy, environmental policy manager at
Mercury, and Andrew Fairbairn, environmental policy
manager at Meridian.
Just to hit the highlights of the written submission, starting with this.
Firstly, acknowledging that reform of the Conservation Act is long overdue
and is strongly supported.
The legislation is outdated, unnecessarily complex, and poorly drafted.
Arguably, it's beyond repair or panel beating, and
broader reform is needed to align with the RMA reform programme, but
that's a story for another day. As matters stand, ESEG supports,
in particular, the simplification of the planning system, the national
conservation policy statement for all types of conservation land, and a single
layer of area-based plans and secondly, the improvements to the
concessions process,
fitting time frames for completion, provision for standardized conditions, and
exempt or pre-approved status. Great innovations.
The Conservation Act planning and concession processes are
critical to ensuring an affordable supply
of clean energy in New Zealand.
Mm.
And the government's commitment to doubling the supply of clean, affordable
energy under Electrify New Zealand is directly
engaged in this context. Little-known fact, breaking news,
but as Christina will share with you,
some 60%
of New Zealand's total electricity generation capacity and
output
is contingent and utterly reliant on access
to the conservation estate.
Oh, wow.
With this firmly in mind, ESEG seeks a number of further, but important, changes to
the drafting of the bill. Firstly, a new function for the department addressing
climate change mitigation and adaptation.
This would not only recognize that threatened flora and fauna, along
with huts and tracks and visitor facilities, roading are at risk from
climate change, but provide the platform for decision
making involving renewable electricity generation, or REG assets, on
conservation land. It would also,
I might add, be better aligned perhaps to the existing departmental functions than
maximizing economic opportunities per se.
That's the first thing, new function.
Second thing, a form of legal instrument for existing, that's existing,
REG assets on the estate, and I'll come to that, and provision for
REG activities involving existing assets to be exempt or pre-approved,
applying what we'll refer to as the activity cascade,
with the concessions process managing the effects around the ongoing
operation of the existing assets.
I'll hand over to Christina now to flesh out the point I've
just made about 60%, and I think you've got a handout that I'd like you all to have
in front of you.
We've got maps.
Yes, and the maps in particular. Go, Christina.
Go, Christina.
Thanks, Martin.
So I just want to give the committee a sense of the scale of the renewable
electricity generation's existing interaction with public
conservation land. It's not simply whether or not the power
station sits on DOC land. Rather, in practice, it's
much more about the generation scheme's reliance on supporting
infrastructure that sits on, under, over,
or is accessed through public conservation land.
So that might be a tunnel, a canal, a water intake,
an electricity cable, or a communications cable,
geothermal pipeline, monitoring equipment, or
simply an access road or a bridge through public conservation
land. It also includes routine activities needed to
keep a generation scheme operating safely,
access for inspections, maintenance, vegetation management,
and replacing aging equipment.
Those supporting activities generally require some form of
approval from DOC,
usually through the concession system.
Sure.
The scale of that interaction is
significant. The renewable generation assets identified in our
submission, which you'll see on the maps in front of you,
interact with the conservation estate, are associated with around
26,500 gigawatt hours of electricity each year,
about 60% of New Zealand's annual generation.
Wow.
Interesting.
Mercury's Rotokawa geothermal operations are a really good
example. The scheme interacts with public conservation land
through geothermal wells, pipelines, transmission, and
fiber optic infrastructure, monitoring sites, and
access. In one case, we had to apply for a
concession for geothermal drilling that passed
beneath the Rotokawa conservation area
without any surface disturbance on the conservation land.
What may look like a relatively minor concession for access,
monitoring a cable or a pipeline, can actually be an
important link in the operating arrangements needed to keep an
existing generation scheme working safely and reliably.
So the key point is, public conservation land and the approvals
needed to use it for these supporting activities are
already an important dependency for a significant part of New
Zealand's renewable electricity supply.
That means secure, workable access to public conservation land
is not just an administrative issue for individual generators,
it can directly affect the safe and reliable operation of a significant
part of New Zealand's electricity system.
And Andrew is going to take you through a particular example-
Yeah, that'd be good
... operating easements.
Good afternoon. Thanks, Christina.
The key issue I wish to canvas with you today is the necessity
of ensuring the terms and conditions of existing operating easements
prevail in cases where crown
ownership is moved from LINZ to the Department of Conservation.
This is something
that is an issue that's in play at the moment, and in EC's
view,
requires legislative change and the Conservation Amendment Act to provide certainty
in the context of the use of those operating easements.
So operating easements, in essence, are instruments that
were created at the time respective hydro schemes throughout the country
were developed. And
provide for maintenance upgrades, ongoing scheme development and lake level
management on land the scheme operator doesn't own.
I think it's an important
point we're going to draw out. EC's position is that the land or subject operating
easements should not be transferred into the conservation state
unless those easement terms remain fully effective and prevail in any
conflict.
Without this protection, conservation management requirements will likely conflict
with existing generation rights.
The practical risk is delay, constraint, or extra
approvals for routine maintenance, upgrades affecting nationally significant
renewable electricity infrastructure.
And as we speak today, this is particularly relevant in the
context of the Waitaki Power Scheme, where transfers are
proposed adjacent to Lake Pukaki and the OLC canal,
and they're going to be reclassified as Scenic Reserve.
Now, Meridian has been engaging with officials around the need to address
this through a legislative fix, but it's fair to say that hasn't been
progressed to date. And effectively, I think this is the opportunity that that
can be done quite simply.
So the proposed solution, the principle I'm really talking about, is really
straightforward. Transferring land into the conservation state should not
reduce, qualify, or undermine the existing operating easement rights.
The preferred solution is a clear statutory protection confirming
existing operating easements prevail over any inconsistent requirement under the
Conservation Act, National Conservation Policy Statement, or area
plan. And we've provided a solution on Appendix
G to our submissions in relation to amendments to, I think, Section
3A of the act.
Alternatively, the bill could provide for a targeted renewable electricity
asset instrument, agreed with the operator and approved by the
minister, which Martin will talk to shortly.
Yeah, just picking up on that.
Concessions as a form of approval give you both a property right and their
environmental permission. Dealing with the form of the property or the issue, the
property right side, concessions are really a poor fit for the type of
assets that Christina took you through.
These assets are not like smaller scale, less engineered structures, which the
concessions framework was really designed for trades, businesses,
occupations of a tourism type nature.
Those assets also predate the concessions process.
So what's set out in the submission is a
bespoke form of property right called a renewable electricity
asset instrument, which would be a hybrid lease and easement.
And, and the reason I say the concessions process doesn't work very well is
that it's got restrictions on exclusive position, but it's absolutely vital
for safety and security. It's got restrictions on the duration of concessions,
30 years, unless exceptional circumstances.
These assets last for up to 100 years.
Mm.
And there's, there's provisions in there where if you're, if you're in the act,
even the amended act, if you're in conflict with a single section of the
Conservation Act or the NCPS, game over, fatal, can't be
granted. So we're positing a bespoke,
um-
Yeah
... asset, uh, instrument for that purpose.
And then sitting aside, alongside that would be the activity cascade that I talked
about earlier,
where the ongoing management of the assets, uh,
and its effects would be provided for under the NCPS.
Generally, whereby ancillary activities would be permitted, in other words,
exempt or pre-approved. Um, the, uh, if you didn't adopt
that REAI, the, the, um,
asset instrument, you would equally, uh, provide for all
existing assets, that 60%, to be exempt or pre-approved, and then
the concession applications go on and provide for the management and
would give direction, uh, the NCPS would need to give direction about whether those
applications are notified or not.
Um, the final thing, and that would be as appropriate to the conservation area.
The final thing I'll say on that is the issue of referring these to an allocation
process is a big concern, and there needs to be clear direction in the NCPS.
If you're going to put these assets up into a competitive situation with other
competing resources, uh, that might get first dibs to,
um, resources on which those assets are critically dependent, then you're, you are
totally undermining security, uh, security of electricity supply in the country.
Final thing before questions is there are a number of minor improvements, uh,
to the, uh, al- already inherent improvements to the concessions
process traversed in the body of the submission to ensure they operate as
efficiently and effectively as intended. Take any questions. Thank you.
Thank you. Look, really powerful submission, and, you know, really puts it in
context for us in terms of how important this legislation and these changes
are. Um,
I just wanted to have a quick question, if I may, at the start.
Um, you know, you talk about all these case studies and obviously the access and,
and in terms of electricity generation.
I mean, have you quantified the cost at all to the energy sector
in terms of-
Great question. Thank you
... how much this is, is costing? Because it must be huge.
It's difficult to quantify-
Yeah
... an opportunity cost, isn't it?
Mm.
But, um-
Yeah
Every year, a process like a Wildlife Act approval or conservation concession is
delayed, and they can take an infinite amount of time.
Mm.
Is another year that electricity prices don't come down.
Yeah.
Yeah. So it is quite significant, but I haven't got
a number around it, unless you've got anything off the top of your head.
No, not off the top of my head.
Look, we've got a few questions. Scott.
Yeah. No, thank you. And of course, we do recognize the birth of the
environmental movement came out of Manapōuri-
Influence
... which is conservation estate with our
jewel of our generation assets hosted there.
So thinking about how we can improve
things, obviously, if we've got existing assets, we need to
make sure, modified landscapes, we need to make sure that they are retained.
That seems
straightforward.
You have made the point that there should
be climate change mitigation and
adaptation
over the economic imperative in the bill.
That's going to assist, I would imagine,
retaining the energy
assets that we need.
Would you like to elaborate on that and why this is so important?
Because this looks to be an easy fix.
Yes.
The reality is that renewable energy is New Zealand's best
shot at climate change mitigation.
Mm.
Mm-hmm.
And equally, a distributed electricity network is critical
to climate change resilience. We're not saying put that over the economic, we're
just saying it's a new purpose that should be put into the mix.
Manapōuri shows you that REG can live in harmony-
Mm-hmm
... with one of the most pristine and significant
natural resource areas in the country.
So, that's for the asset, and that's what we're talking about, protecting the
existing asset. But the ongoing management of effects, that's where the concessions
process comes in-
Mm
... and ensures that that remains responsive and alive to particular issues that
are arising in environmental context.
So, that's where the effects side of it and that ongoing living in harmony
can be addressed.
Thank you. Grant.
Yeah, I'm just trying to understand.
You say for some of the land and the assets to be
transferred from LINZ to DOC, is there a
particular rationale for that? I'm just trying to understand, because that seems to
have created some issues that didn't exist before.
Yeah. So
in essence, and in the context of the Waitaki situation, the land
has been reviewed from the point of view, first of all, from
an ownership perspective, and then there's obviously been discussions between LINZ
and the Department of Conservation around saying these particular parcels of
land have, and some of them are hundreds of hectares,
have conservation values and therefore let's move them to the conservation estate.
Now, our view is, if that happens, what we
don't want to get into the situation is where we can operate freely at the moment,
suddenly we're confronted with constraints.
And as I said, I think there is an easy fix, and that is
suggested in the paper in Appendix G from a legislative point of
view.
But in the event that that doesn't occur,
as I said, our first preference would be that those kind of exchanges don't occur
because of the-
Very quick. So have you obviously consulted with ministers on this?
We've consulted officials and people within LINZ and written.
And I think the last kind of engagement we had was kind of, "Well, this process is
coming up. Can't really talk to you about it now, but you should be using this
process to bring the issue to the floor."
Okay. Thank you.
If that's helpful or not.
Yeah, no, very helpful.
Look, thank you. We have met time. We appreciate your time and
wow, what a valuable submission. A lot to take on board there.
So thank you.
Thank you.
Thanks for your time.
Yeah. Thanks. Good to see you, man.
Oh,
I'm sorry.
Oh, yes. Yep. So,
we
will now just bring officials on. Are they online?